Finding Aid for Gilbert E. Bursley papers, 1960-1981
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Gilbert E. Bursley papers 1960-1981
Bursley, Gilbert E.
18 linear feet
8548 Aa 2
Republican state senator, president of Cleary College; legislative files and miscellaneous materials from his tenure as Cleary College president.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Gilbert E. Bursley (donor no. 6264 ) and came to the library in various accessions.
The collection is open to research.
Gilbert E. Bursley was born in Ann Arbor, Michigan, February 28, 1913. He was educated at the University of Michigan (A.B., 1934) and the Harvard Business School (M.B.A., 1936). Prior to his election to the Michigan State House of Representatives in 1960, Bursley had a varied career in the military as military attaché in Turkey after World War II, as United Nations peacekeeping observer in the Middle East in the 1950s, and as United States Information Agency head in portions of Africa.
Returning to Michigan, he served as chairman of the Ann Arbor Republican Party, 1958-1959, then in 1960, he won election to the Michigan House, serving two terms, then in 1964, he was elected to the Michigan Senate, where he served until 1978. After leaving office, he became president of Cleary College in Ypsilanti, Michigan. He died in September 1998.
The Gilbert Bursley collection consists of Legislative files, primarily from the period when he served in the Michigan State Senate. These files consist of newsletters and news releases, correspondence from constituents, and reference files maintained as background information on issues of the day. These files also include a record of the bills that Bursley introduced and his interest in the activities of various state and regional boards, commissions, and agencies. A smaller portion of the collection details some of his interests as president of Cleary College after his left the Legislature.
Subjects:
Abortion--Law and legislation--Michigan.; Birth control--Law and legislation--Michigan.; Cleary College (Ypsilanti, Mich.); Education--Michigan.; Michigan. Legislature.; Republican Party (Mich.)
- Biographical
  - Clippings and other materials (Box 1)
- Legislative file
  - Newsletters, news releases 1960-1978 (Box 1)
    (also include tabulations of constituent questionnaires)
  - Correspondence largely with legislators and other public officials 1974-1978 (Box 1)
  - Alphabetical files
    - A (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor Township (Box 2)
    - Augustus Township (Box 2)
    - B (Box 2)
    - Brighton (Box 2)
    - C (Box 2)
    - Chelsea (Box 2)
    - Clinton (Box 2)
    - D (Box 2)
    - Dexter (Box 2)
    - Dexter Township (Box 2)
    - E (Box 2)
    - F (Box 2)
    - G (Box 2)
    - H (Box 2)
    - Hagerhorst, D. Joann (Box 2)
    - Howell (Box 2)
    - I (Box 2)
    - J (Box 2)
    - Jackson County (Box 2)
    - K (Box 2)
    - L (Box 2)
    - Livingston (Box 2)
    - M (Box 2)
    - N (Box 3)
    - O (Box 3)
    - P (Box 3)
    - Pinckney (Box 3)
    - Pittsfield Township (Box 3)
    - Q (Box 3)
    - R (Box 3)
    - S (Box 3)
    - Salem Township (Box 3)
    - Saline (Box 3)
    - Superior Township (Box 3)
    - T (Box 3)
    - U (Box 3)
    - V (Box 3)
    - W (Box 4)
    - Washtenaw County (Box 4)
    - Whitmore Lake (Box 4)
    - Ypsilanti (Box 4)
    - York Township (Box 4)
    - Z (Box 4)
  - Reference file
    - Abortion (Box 4)
    - Attorney General's opinion (Box 4)
    - Campaign (Box 4)
    - Con-Con 1978 (Box 4)
    - Consumer Protection (Box 4)
    - Delegates-Republican State Convention 1976 (Box 4)
    - Delegates-Republican State Convention 1978 (Box 4)
    - District (Box 5)
    - Drug Abuse (Box 5)
    - Eastern Michigan University (Box 5)
    - Energy (Box 5)
    - Environment (Box 5)
    - Equal Rights Amendments (Box 5)
    - Form letters (Box 5)
    - Fund Raiser February 8, 1978 (Box 5)
    - Intermediate School Districts (Box 5)
    - International Trade, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Interns (Box 5)
    - John Knox Retirement Village (Box 6)
    - Legislative Dinner 1971-1977, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - Legislative districts (Box 6)
    - Mass transportation, 2 folders (Box 6)
      (see also Transportation folder)
    - Medicaid (Box 6)
    - Michigan Flag (Box 6)
    - Michigan International Council (Box 6)
    - Michigan Youth International (Box 6)
    - Michigan Week (Box 6)
    - Midwest Compact (Box 6)
    - Mill Creek Park, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Mill Creek Park, 2 volumes (Box 7)
    - National Organization for Women (NOW) (Box 7)
    - News releases and newsletters 1960-1978, 5 folders (Box 7)
    - News clippings, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Ovendale-Gagetown (Box 7)
    - PBB, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Pesticides (Box 7)
    - Pirgim (Box 7)
    - Planned Parenthood-Washtenaw County (Box 7)
    - Population, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Population (Box 8)
    - Portage Lake (Box 8)
    - Proposal C (Box 8)
    - Public Health Statute Revision Project (Box 8)
    - Questionnaires, 5 folders (Box 8)
    - Republican Party (Box 8)
    - Republican State Central Committee (Box 8)
    - Resolutions 1965-1972 (Box 8)
    - Science and Technology, 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Single Business Tax, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Speeches, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Tax Limitation (Box 10)
    - Taxes (Box 10)
    - Transportation (Box 10)
    - United Nations Day, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Universite Internacional (Box 10)
    - Vandalism in School (Box 10)
    - Wayne State University Center for Professional Development in Teaching and Learning (Box 10)
    - Women (Box 10)
    - Women's Liberation Movement (Box 10)
    - Workmen's Compensation (Box 11)
    - Ypsilanti State Hospital (Box 11)
    - Ypsilanti State Hospital-Forensic Center (Box 11)
    - Zero Population Growth (Box 11)
  - Bills Introduced
    - 1971-1972 (Box 11)
    - 1973-1974, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - 1975 (Box 12)
    - 1976 (Box 12)
    - 1977 (Box 12)
    - School Aid bill, S.B.1495 (clippings) (Box 12)
    - Headlight Bill, S.B.1021 (Box 12)
    - Abortion, S.B. 345 (Box 12)
  - Boards and Commissions
    - Ann Arbor Chamber of Commerce-Education Committee (Box 12)
    - Artrain (Box 12)
    - Health and Social Services
      - General (Box 12)
      - Aging, 2 folders (Box 12)
      - Mental Health Code (Box 12)
      - Emergency Medical Services (Box 12)
      - Nursing Homes (Box 12)
      - Malpractice Insurance (Box 12)
    - Huron River Planning Group (Box 12)
    - Huron River Watershed Council (Box 12)
    - Intergovernmental Cooperation, Commission on (Box 12)
    - Michigan Energy and Resource Research Association, 3 folders (Box 13)
    - Michigan Council for the Arts (Box 13)
    - Michigan Education Council (Box 13)
    - Michigan International Council (Box 13)
    - Michigan Partners of the Americas, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Right to Read (Box 14)
    - SEMCOG (South East Michigan Council of Governments) (Box 14)
    - SEMTA (South Eastern Michigan Transportation Authority) (Box 14)
    - Telecommunications (Box 14)
    - Telecommunications Advisory Commission (Box 14)
    - Transportation Quadrant Committee (Box 14)
    - United Nations, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Visiting Committee (Box 14)
    - (Michigan) Women's Commission (Box 14)
  - Senate Committee background files
    - School finance (Box 15)
    - Population Growth in Michigan (Box 15)
    - Abortion Law Reform (Box 15)
    - Education of gifted and handicapped children (Box 15)
    - Consumer protection in education (Box 15)
    - Students and collective bargaining (Box 16)
    - Teachers and collective bargaining (Box 16)
    - Career Education (Box 16)
    - Compensatory Education Program (Box 16)
    - National Assessment and competency tests (Box 16)
    - Early childhood education (Box 16)
  - Thank you letters from constituents (Box 16)
- Cleary College Background files
  - Fund for the improvement of Postsecondary Education (Box 16)
  - Michigan Educational Council (Box 16)
  - Michigan Education Seminars (Box 16)
  - Michigan Energy and Resource Association (Box 16)
  - National Assessment of Educational Progress (Box 16)
  - Education Commission of the States 1976-1980 (Box 17)
  - Interstate Migrant Education Task Force 1978-1980 (Box 17)
  - National Assessment of Educational Progress 1979-1980 (Box 17)
  - Assessment Policy Committee 1977-1980 (Box 17)
  - Michigan Vocational Education Task Force 1979-1980 (Box 17)
  - Fund for Improvement of Post-secondary Education 1979-1980 (Box 18)
  - Higher Education Capital Investment Advisory Committee 1979-1980, 3 folders (Box 18)
  - Michigan International Council 1980-1981 (Box 18)
  - Michigan Vocational Education Task Force 1980 (Box 18)
  - United Nations Day 1979-1980 (Box 18)
  - Artrain 1979-1981, 3 folders (Box 18)
  - National Assessment of Educational Progress 1980 (Box 18)